Guide to the Arthur Weindorf Subway Collection 1903-1945, 1973-1974, undated (bulk 1925-1935) PR 127
New-York Historical Society
Arthur Weindorf Subway Collection
1903-1945, 1973-1974, undated
New-York Historical Society
PR 127
3.43 Linear feet (4 boxes)
Photographs and clippings related to the New York City subway system, collected by subway engineer Arthur Weindorf. Photostats of subway posters and maps are included.
Provenance
Gift of Mrs. Mabel Davidson, June 1979.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to thirty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. See guidelines in Print Room for details.
Biographical Note
Born in Long Island City, Arthur Weindorf (1885- 1979)was a practicing cartoonist in his early years. From 1908 to 1944 he worked as an architectural designer and engineer for the City of New York's Public Service Commission (the precursor to today's New York City Transit Authority.) During his tenure at the Public Service Commission, Weindorf collected drawings, clippings, maps, posters, and photographs of the New York City subway. In 1916 he built the first New York City subway model; his later models were displayed at the 1939-40 World's Fair. In addition to models, Weindorf also created illustrations, maps, certificates, and paintings for the Commission. Weindorf's non-subway-related artistic work was widely exhibited during his lifetime.
Scope and Content Note
The Arthur Weindorf Subway Collection spans the period from 1903-1974 and primarily contains photographs and photostats of drawings, models, and maps created by Arthur Weindorf during his tenure at the Public Service Commission. Also included are photographs taken by Public Service Commission photographers during the construction of the New York City subway system. The collection is divided into six series: Drawings and Models; Subway Maps and Posters; Clippings; Subway Construction Photographs; Miscellaneous Materials; and Negatives.
After Arthur Weindorf's death, his daughter gave 259 items to the New-York Historical Society, all of which were numbered by the staff with Weindorf's initials; i.e. "AW17." Several newspaper clippings and eighteen negatives, which came with the same gift, were not numbered. Many of the numbered items were dispersed into other collections in the Department of Prints, Photographs, and Architectural Collections; ten of these numbered items remain dispersed among other collections. As the numbering system did not appear to correspond to any sort of organization of the materials, the material was rearranged at the time of processing. An original numbered list is available in the department's Collection File.
Arrangement
The collection is divided into six series:
Missing Title
Series I. Drawings and Models
Series II. Subway Maps and Posters
Series III. Clippings
Series IV. Subway Construction Photographs
Series V. Miscellaneous Materials
Series VI. Negatives
Related Material at the Department of Prints, Photographs, and Architectural Collections
Other photographs of the construction of the New York City subway can be found in the Subway Construction Photograph Collection (PR 069) and the New York Subway Negative Collection (PR 232).
Glass negatives.; Clippings (information artifacts); negatives (photographs); Prints (visual works).; Photographic prints.; Line-route maps; Municipal engineering -- New York (State) -- New York.; New York (N.Y.) -- Pictorial works.; Local transit -- New York (State) -- New York.; Subway stations -- New York (State) -- New York.; Tunnels -- New York (State) -- New York.; Subways -- New York (State) -- New York.; New York (State). Public Service Commission
- Series I: Drawings and Models
  Scope and Contents note
  Series I includes photographs and photostats of Weindorf's original work for the Public Service Commission. Drawings and models of subway tunnels, subway stations, subway line extensions, and other subway-related engineering issues can be found here. Many photos of drawings are mounted on thick brown scrapbook paper, with some items affixed to the verso.
  Titles are transcribed, or, if in brackets, were assigned during processing. All sketches are by Weindorf unless otherwise noted. The series is divided into two subseries: Drawings and Illustrations; and Models and Exhibits; thereunder, items are arranged by date, if known.
  - Subseries I: Drawings and Illustrations
    - Cross-Sections
      - "Underground Railroad in front of the Grand Central Station, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - "7th Ave. bet. 53rd & 54th Sts. ", 1917 (Box 1, Folder 1)
        General note
        [3 copies]
      - "Beekman Street East of Nassau Street", 1917 (Box 1, Folder 1)
        [2 copies]
      - "Underpinning the IRT Subway in Park Row", 1919 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - [42nd St. at Fifth Ave.], 1922 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - [Along Sixth Ave., starting subway construction,], [1920-1929] (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - "Section through 33rd Street at Sixth Avenue and Broadway,", 1931 (Box 1, Folder 1)
        [4 copies]
      - "190th St. Overlook Terrace Station Looking South", 1939 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Stations
      - [Proposed kiosk entrance], 1912 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - "Mosholu Parkway Station" (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - "Woodlawn Station", 1915 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - [Subway entrances, 42nd St. in front of Grand Central] [2 copies], 1920 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - "149th Street Subway Station", 1924 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - "Station on Eighth Ave. between 40th and 44th St.", 1929 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - "Fulton St. Station of Nassau-Broad St. Subway", 1930 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - "Queensboro Plaza Station", undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Tracks
      - "Times Square Station" [4 copies], 1920 (Box 1, Folder 3)
        See also: Box 4, folder 25
      - "Proposed Rapid Transit line" [in suburban districts], 1921 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - "Flexing of tracks at 53rd St. and Eighth Ave.", 1928 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - [Flexing at Smith St. and Schermerhorn St.], 1928 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - "Transit Facilities in Vicinity of 34th and Broadway" [2 copies], 1932 (Box 1, Folder 3)
        See: Box 4, folder 25
      - "Passageway between 149th St. IRT Subway Station," [3 copies], 1937 (Box 1, Folder 3)
        See Box 4, folder 25
      - "Proposed modification of Kingsbridge Road Underpass", 1937 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - "Underground Times Square", 1944 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - "ProposedReconstruction of present Rapid Transit Subway", undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Tunnels
      - "Corner of Clark and Fulton Sts.," by P. P. Pullis and Weindorf, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - "Willoughby Street Tubes," by P. P. Pullis and Weindorf, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - "Corner of Old Slip and South St." and "Corner of Old Slip and Front St.," by P. P. Pullis and Weindorf, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - [42nd St. looking toward Times Square], 1922 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - "Fulton St. at Water St.", 1928 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - "Tubes under river bottom between Manhattan and Welfare Island,", 1928 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - [Tunnels crossing at Church & Fulton Sts.], 1928 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - [O'Rourke Twin tunnels] [2 copies], undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Vehicular Tunnels, Mid-town Tunnel
      - "Mid-town Vehicular Tunnels, Long Island City Plaza, Scheme No. 4" [2 copies], [1920] (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - "Mid-town Vehicular tunnels and Hudson River Vehicular Tunnels, West Side Plazas", 1930 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - "Mid-town Vehicular Tunnels, Long Island City Plaza", 1930 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - "Mid-town Vehicular Tunnels, Long Island City Plaza, Scheme No. 2" / on verso: "Cross Section of Nassau St. Looking south", 1930 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - "Mid-town Vehicular Tunnels, Long Island City Plaza, Scheme No. 3" / on verso: "IRT line at Wall and William Sts.", 1930 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Miscellaneous
      - "Proposed Memorial Bridge connecting boroughs of Brooklyn & Richmond", 1920 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - "Design of a Typical Building, New York World's Fair", 1939 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - [Underground subway construction] [2 copies], 1940 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - "Bomb Proof Shelter", 1941 (Box 1, Folder 6)
        See Box 4, folder 26
      - [Retirement certificate for William Siebert], 1941 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - "Trackway Shelter, Lexington Ave., Manhattan" [2 copies], 1942 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - "Proposed Modification of the City Hall El. Station", 1944 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - [Retirement certificate for Dr. John J. Moorhead], 1944 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - [Retirement certificate for Ralph Russell Monroe], 1944 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - "City of New York Substation 2", undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - "Subway Air Raid Shelter", undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - MODELS AND EXHIBITS
    - Cross-Sections
      - [74th St. and Lexington Ave.] [3 copies] / on verso: "Mid-town Vehicular Tunnels, East Side Plaza", [1915] (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - [Weindorf with model showing 8th Avenue Subway], 1932 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Roads
      - [Grand Central Diagonal Station site], [1915] (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - [Pittsburgh, new highway proposal] [2 copies], 1930 (Box 1, Folder 8)
        See also: Box 4, folder 27
      - [Several blocks of houses with overpass] [2 copies], 1931 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - [Proposed viaduct across Bronx Park], 1938 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - "Proposed improvement to Brooklyn Bridge", 1941 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - [Bushwick Yards], undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - [Riverside Park], undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
        See Box 4, folder 27
      - [Underpass at Grand Concourse] [2 copies], undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - [Washington Heights area of Manhattan], undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - [West Side Highway] [2 copies], undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Stations
      - [125th and Lexington Ave. Station] [2 copies], [1915] (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - "34th St. Station, Route No. 101" [4 copies], 1931 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - "City Subway Structures at Fourth Avenue and 10th St., Brooklyn," World's Fair exhibit, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - [Fourth Avenue Viaduct at Smith Street, Brooklyn], undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - "Underground subways at Times Square", undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Tunnels
      - [Midtown Tunnel tubes], 1930 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Miscellaneous
      - [Weindorf in cutaway subway car], World's Fair exhibit / on verso: "IRT and BMT subway structures at Times Square," World's Fair exhibit, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - [World's Fair Exhibit], 1939 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Series II: Subway Maps and Posters
  Series II includes a number of posters and maps Weindorf designed for the Public Service Commission which may have been used as advertisements in subway cars and buses. They describe how to take the subway to various points of interest in New York City, such as the Cloisters, the Museum of Natural History, and the World's Fair grounds in Flushing, Queens. One poster details how to get to the "New York Municipal Airport Laguardia Field" by subway and bus. Weindorf designed many of the standard subway route maps used by the PSC in the 1930s and 1940s. Several of these maps appear here, including one with the routes of the IRT lines and another with those of the IND lines.
  Titles are transcribed, or, if in brackets, were assigned during processing. The series is divided into two subseries: Maps; and Posters; thereunder, items are arranged by date, if known.
  - MAPS
    - [New York subway lines], 1918 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - "Routes of the Interborough Rapid Transit Company," drawn by D. L. Turner & Weindorf [2 copies], 1920 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - "Proposed Rapid Transit Lines" / on verso: "A Real Home at Robin Wood, Beechurst, Flushing,", 1922 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - [Rapid Transit Lines (Subway and Elevated)], 1922 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - "Location of Stations - Independent City-Owned Rapid Transit Railroad,", 1936 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      See Box 4, folder 28
    - "Station Guide, New York City Transit System, IND Division", [1939-40] (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - "Station Guide, New York City Transit System, IND Division," [2 copies], [1941-45] (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - POSTERS
    - "American Museum of Natural History", [1935] (Box 1, Folder 12)
      See Box 4, folder 29
    - "Fort Tryon Parkand the Cloisters" [2 copies], [1935] (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - "New York Municipal Airport Laguardia Field", undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Series III: Clippings
  Series III. contains newspaper and magazine clippings and articles. A series of articles about Weindorf in the Queens County Times from September 1973 to December 1974 details his life and reproduces some of his early cartoon and postcard drawings. Also included are three issues of the Interborough Bulletin, from 1913 to 1915. Several other clippings feature Weindorf's sketches of subway routes and stations.
  - "The Joys of Subway Building" [1922 Sketch published Dec. 1923 in a New York State Transportation Commission publication] (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Weindorf with model of apartment house, photo published in Herald Tribune, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Clipping from New York World-Telegram, April 25, 1936, painting by Weindorf shown (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - "Section through 33rd Street at Sixth Avenue and Broadway," drawing reproduced in Architectural Record, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - "An under-river shield Tunnel which is being constructed without gravel packing," drawing by John F. O'Rourke, published in The Bulletin. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Clippings from the Interborough Bulletin, 1913-1915 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Clippings from the Queens County Times, 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Series IV: Subway Construction Photographs
  Series IV contains 110 photographs taken by the Public Service Commission between 1913 and 1938 to document the New York City subway construction. The photographs here are roughly grouped by subject and are mostly underground views. Weindorf may have used these photographs as visual sources for his drawings and models, especially those photographs of tunnels. Researchers should consult the Print Room's Subway Construction Photograph Collection (PR 069) for a description of these photographs.
  - Equipment - 9 photos, 1917-1932 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Stations - 6 photos, 1924-1932 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Street Scenes - 15 photos, 1926-1930 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Tracks - 8 photos, 1916-1936 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Trains and trolley cars - 9 photos, 1924-[1940] (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Tunnels - 26 photos, 1913-1938 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Underground scenes - 31 photos, 1919-1938 (Box 1, Folder 21-22)
  - Miscellaneous - 6 photos, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Series V: Miscellaneous Materials
  Series V includes what appear to be Weindorf's personal snapshots, as well as a chart showing public investment in transportation from 1860-1920. The snapshots date from 1903 and one shows children playing. A panoramic photograph of the west side of Manhattan island is also included in this series.
  - "Burden's Woods, 1903" [snapshot of children] (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - "Ravenswoods 1903, where bridge comes across in Queens" [snapshot of snowscape] (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - [Chart showing investment in transportation from 1860-1920] (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - [Panoramic View along riverbank], photo, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    See Box 4, folder 30
  - [House], cyanotype [4 variations], undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Series VI. Negatives
  Series VI is comprised of both glass and film negatives. All but two are 8 x 10 inches. The two 11 x 14 negatives are both of subway route maps drawn by Weindorf in 1920. Most of the other negatives are images of Weindorf's models.
  Negatives are organized by medium. All models are by Weindorf.
  - Subseries I: FILM
    - "Concrete Block Tunnels" model (2 copies), unadted (Box 2)
    - "Concrete Block Tunnels for roadways and R.R. traffic. O'Rourke Construction CO.," model, undated (Box 2)
    - [Lower part of Manhattan] model, undated (Box 2)
    - "Modernization of North River Waterfront," model, undated (Box 2)
  - Subseries II: GLASS
    - "Tubes under river bottom between Manhattan and Welfare Island," photo of drawing, 1928 (Box 2)
    - [Midtown Tunnel tubes], model, 1930 (Box 2)
    - [Riverside Drive Sewage] model, undated (Box 2)
    - [Riverside Drive] model, undated (Box 2)
    - [110th Street Syphon Sewer] model, undated (Box 2)
    - [Grand Central Station] model, made for exhibition by [New York] City in Albany, undated (Box 2)
    - [Construction under Hanson Place M. E. Church] model, undated (Box 2)
    - [Lexington Avenue and 125th Street] model, undated (Box 2)
    - "Underground subways at Times Square," model, undated (Box 2)
    - [Canal Street Crosstown Subway] model, undated (Box 2)
    - [Broadway at Canal Street] model, undated (Box 2)
    - "Routes of the New York Municipal Railway Corp.," map, 1920 (Box 3)
    - "Routes of the Interborough Rapid Transit Company," map, 1920 (Box 3)
- Oversize Material
  - From Series I: Drawings and Models
    - DRAWINGS AND ILLUSTRATIONS--Tracks
      - "Times Square Station" [4 copies], 1920 (Box 4, Folder 25)
      - "Transit Facilities in Vicinity of 34th and Broadway", 1932 (Box 4, Folder 25)
      - "Passageway between 149th St. IRT Subway Station," [3 copies], 1937 (Box 4, Folder 25)
      - "Proposed modification of Kingsbridge Road Underpass", 1937 (Box 4, Folder 25)
      - "Underground Times Square", 1944 (Box 4, Folder 25)
      - "Proposed Reconstruction of present Rapid Transit Subway", undated (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - DRAWINGS AND ILLUSTRATIONS--Miscellaneous
      - "Bomb Proof Shelter", 1941 (Box 4, Folder 26)
      - [Retirement certificate for William Siebert], 1941 (Box 4, Folder 26)
      - "Trackway Shelter, Lexington Ave., Manhattan" [2 copies], 1942 (Box 4, Folder 26)
      - "Proposed Modification of the City Hall El. Station", 1944 (Box 4, Folder 26)
      - [Retirement certificate for Dr. John J. Moorhead], 1944 (Box 4, Folder 26)
      - [Retirement certificate for Ralph Russell Monroe], 1944 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - MODELS AND EXHIBITS--Roads
      - [Pittsburgh, new highway proposal], 1930 (Box 4, Folder 27)
      - [Riverside Park], undated (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - MODELS AND EXHIBITS--Stations
      - "34th St. Station, Route No. 101" [4 copies], 1931 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - From Series II: Maps and Posters
    - MAPS
      - "Location of Stations - Independent City-Owned Rapid Transit Railroad,", 1936 (Box 4, Folder 28)
      - "Station Guide, New York City Transit System, IND Division", [1939-1940] (Box 4, Folder 28)
      - "Station Guide, New York City Transit System, IND Division," [2 copies], [1941-1945] (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - POSTERS
      - "American Museum of Natural History", [1935] (Box 4, Folder 29)
      - "Fort Tryon Park and the Cloisters" [2 copies], [1935] (Box 4, Folder 29)
      - "New York Municipal Airport Laguardia Field", undated (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - From Series V. Miscellaneous Materials
    - [Panoramic View along riverbank], photo, 1920 (Box 4, Folder 30)